<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>In/Coherent Design on adam-p</title><link>https://adam-p.ca/inco/</link><description>Recent content in In/Coherent Design on adam-p</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://adam-p.ca/inco/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Instructions on the ceiling</title><link>https://adam-p.ca/inco/2021/11/ftnu/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adam-p.ca/inco/2021/11/ftnu/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://fromtheneckupmassage.com/">From the Neck Up&lt;/a> does neck-up massage, including intra-oral. When the RMT has their fingers in your mouth it&amp;rsquo;s pretty hard to give directions. So there are hand signs for communicating with the RMT. And, since you&amp;rsquo;re laying on your back during the procedure, the guide to the signs are posted on the ceiling.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="../img/inco/ftnu.jpg" alt="ceiling sign">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>First Post: someone's last post</title><link>https://adam-p.ca/inco/2017/01/first-post/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adam-p.ca/inco/2017/01/first-post/</guid><description>&lt;p>I often come across digital and physical interface designs that are either great (coherent) or terrible (incoherent). For some mysterious reason I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to capture such interfaces and share them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To start, a curious headstone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The goal of the design of a headstone is to be read by the living. For a few decades some of the people who read it will have known the deceased, but many won&amp;rsquo;t, and after a while no one will have personally known them. The design of this headstone ensures that it will get more reading-attention than an ordinary headstone. I certainly stood in front of it longer than any other, while figuring out how to decipher and read it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s just the right degree of indecipherable. You can instantly tell that there&amp;rsquo;s something there to read and that it probably won&amp;rsquo;t require you to bust out pen and paper to do frequency analysis or ROT-13. It&amp;rsquo;s just hard enough to keep you standing there for a few minutes, and no harder.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="../img/inco/headstone.jpg" alt="headstone">&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>